<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- OPTIONS, known as processing instructions (PIs) go here. -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of PIs,
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use. -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC): -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references: -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space: 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of popular PIs -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-haas-idr-bfd-subcode-01" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.0 -->
  <front>
    <title>BGP Cease Notification Subcode For BFD</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-haas-idr-bfd-subcode-00"/>
    <author fullname="Jeffrey Haas" initials="J" surname="Haas">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jhaas@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2022"/>
    <area/>
    <workgroup>Inter-Domain Routing</workgroup>
    <!-- <keyword/> -->
    <abstract>
      <t>
        The Bidirectional Forwarding Detection protocol (BFD) is used to detect
        loss of connectivity between two forwarding elements, typically with
        low latency.  BFD is leveraged by routing protocols, including the
        Border Gateway Protocol (BGP), to use that detection of loss of
        connectivity to bring down the protocol connections faster than the
        native protocol timers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a Subcode for the BGP Cease NOTIFICATION message
        for when a BGP connection is being closed due to a BFD session going
        down.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note>
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The Bidirectional Forwarding Detection protocol (BFD) <xref target="RFC5880" format="default"/> is used to detect loss of connectivity between two
        forwarding elements, typically with low latency.  BFD is utilized as a
        service for various clients, including routing protocols, to provide an
        advisory mechanism for those clients to take action when a BFD session
        goes down <xref target="RFC5882" format="default"/>.  This is typically used by the
        clients to take faster action in terminating their connections than the
        native protocol timers might allow.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Border Gateway Protocol, Version 4 (BGP) <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/>
        terminates its sessions upon Hold Timer expiration when the speaker does
        not receive a BGP message within the negotiated Hold Time interval.
        The minimum Hold Time interval supported by the protocol is three
        seconds. The Hold Timer may be optionally negotiated to being disabled
        with a Hold Time interval of zero.
      </t>
      <t>
        If a BGP speaker desires to have its sessions terminate faster
        than the supported BGP Hold Timer can accommodate upon loss of
        connectivity, BFD is used to supply that faster detection.  When the
        BFD session state changes to Down, the BGP speaker terminates the session.
        BGP will send a NOTIFICATION message, if possible, and then close the
        TCP connection for the session.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>BFD Cease NOTIFICATION Subcode</name>
      <t>
        The value (TBD) has been allocated by IANA for the "BFD Down" Cease
        NOTIFICATION message Subcode.
      </t>
      <t>
        When a BGP session is terminated due to a BFD session going into the
        Down state, the BGP Speaker SHOULD send a NOTIFICATION message with the
        Error Code Cease and the Error Subcode "BFD Down".
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>
        A BFD session may go Down when there is only a partial loss of
        connectivity between two BGP Speakers.  Operators using BFD for their
        BGP sessions make choices for what BFD timers are used based on a
        variety of inputs for stability vs. fast failure depending on the role
        BGP is playing for the deployment.
      </t>
      <t>
        In the event of a BGP session being terminated due to a BFD Down event
        from partial loss of connectivity as detected by BFD, the remote BGP
        Speaker might be able to receive the BGP NOTIFICATION message with the
        BFD Down Subcode.  The receiving BGP Speaker will then have an
        understanding that the session is being terminated because of a
        BFD-detected issue and not an issue with the BGP speaker.
      </t>
      <t>
        When there is a total loss of connectivity between two BGP Speakers, it
        may not be possible for the NOTIFICATION message to have been sent.
        Even so, BGP speakers may provide this reason as part of their
        operational state; e.g. bgpPeerLastError in the BGP MIB.
        <xref target="RFC4273" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        When the procedures in <xref target="RFC8538" format="default"/> for sending a
        NOTIFICATION message with a Cease Code and Hard Reset Subcode, and the
        session is being terminated because BFD has gone Down, the BFD Down
        Subcode SHOULD be encapsulated in the Hard Reset's data portion of the
        NOTIFICATION message.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document introduces no additional BGP security considerations.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate a new value from the BGP Cease
        NOTIFICATION message subcodes registry with the Name "BFD Down", and a
        Reference of this document.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Thanks to Jeff Tantsura for his comments on the draft.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5880.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4273.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4486.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5882.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8538.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
